Elwin Huaman, M.Sc.

 ☑ elwinlhq@gmail.com
 y @ElwinHuaman

https://elwin.huamanquispe.com/

in http://www.linkedin.com/in/ElwinHuaman/

https://www.youtube.com/@ElwinHuaman/

I am currently pursuing a Ph.D. in Computer Science, it is strongly focused on knowledge graphs, their creation, curation, and deployment over under-resourced languages. I have working experience in researching, teaching, and the maintenance of knowledge graphs in the industry. Furthermore, I have published several articles and co-authored a book titled *Knowledge graphs: Methodology, Tools and Selected Use Cases*. Moreover, I have participated and been awarded in a conference, hackathon, and datathon. Last but not least, I run several projects, workshops, and presentations related to under-resourced, and endangered languages.

Employment History

Assistant Facilitator, Wikimedia Education, Wikimedia Foundation, Remote.

Support in the management, monitoring, and evaluation of the Training of Trainers for Reading Wikipedia in the Classroom program, as well as ensuring that participants have a smooth learning experience through the program.

2021 – 2022 Lecturer, Advance Topics in Computer Science, Innsbruck University, Austria.

In this practical lesson, students learned and applied their programming and research skill to dive into groundbreaking topics and technologies in computer science, e.g. Knowledge graphs.

Lecturer, Online Communication and Marketing, University of Innsbruck, Austria.

It was focused on learning semantic web technologies, and apply them to online services, e.g., students set up a website, add semantic annotations, and create e-commerce knowledge bases.

Teaching Assistant, Programming Methodology, University of Innsbruck, Austria.

In this pro-seminar, students complement their knowledge of Java programming language.

Moreover, students are evaluated weekly, e.g., through presentations, homework, and quizzes.

2018 – 2022 Researcher, Semantic Technology Institute (STI), University of Innsbruck, Austria.

During this period, I participated in several projects (e.g. MindLab, WordLiftNG), coauthored a book (e.g., Knowledge Graphs), and published several articles (see Google Scholar).

2017 – 2018 **Business Development Consultant.** Crnomelj Information Center, **Slovenia**.

Task: Planning, organizing and implementing activities to promote and develop tourism and business in the Bela Krajina region. In addition, running technology workshops.

2016 – 2017 Lecturer. Research Center of the National University of Altiplano, Puno, Peru.

Task: Training teachers in research areas, and use of technologies such as Mendeley (Bibliographic References Manager), SigmaPlot (Data analysis), and DSpace (Repository of data).

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Science (Ongoing). University of Innsbruck, Austria
Topic: Knowledge Graph Quality Assessment
I research semantic web technologies that can be used for assessing the quality of knowledge graphs, e.g., data modelling, ontologies, knowledge representation, and knowledge curation.

M.Sc. in Web Engineering. University of Oviedo, Spain

I specialized in developing web technologies using programming languages like PHP, Python,

Java, Html, JavaScript. I work on UI design. Also, I did research on semantic web, linked data,

RDF, OWL, ontologies, dictionaries, Linked open data.

M.Sc. in Digital Information Systems. University of Salamanca, Spain

I focused on indexing and retrieval systems for digital information, content management and network analysis in digital environments, description, representation, diffusion, consumption, preservation, and organization of digital content.

Education (continued)

2008 – 2012

■ B.Sc. in Systems Engineering. National University of Altiplano - Puno, Peru My interests were focused on implementing and optimizing complex systems, databases management, and content management systems (CMS). e.g., A platform for managing students and teachers data of the University of Altiplano.

Languages

English Professional working proficiency

Spanish Native or bilingual proficiency

Quechua Native or bilingual proficiency

Italian Limited working proficiency

German | Elementary proficiency

Research Publications

Books and Chapters

Fensel, D., Simsek, U., Angele, K., Huaman, E., Kärle, E., Panasiuk, O., ... Wahler, A. (2020). Knowledge graphs - methodology, tools and selected use cases. Ø doi:10.1007/978-3-030-37439-6

Conference Proceedings

- Huaman, E., & Fensel, D. (2021). Knowledge graph curation: A practical framework. In *Ijckg'21: The 10th international joint conference on knowledge graphs, virtual event, thailand, december 6 8, 2021* (pp. 166–171).

 Odoi:10.1145/3502223.3502247
- Huaman, E., Tauqeer, A., & Fensel, A. (2021). Towards knowledge graphs validation through weighted knowledge sources. In Knowledge graphs and semantic web third iberoamerican conference and second indo-american conference, KGSWC 2021, kingsville, texas, usa, november 22-24, 2021, proceedings (Vol. 1459, pp. 47-60). Odi:10.1007/978-3-030-91305-2_4

Journal Articles

- Simsek, U., Kärle, E., Angele, K., Huaman, E., Opdenplatz, J., Sommer, D., ... Fensel, D. (2023). A knowledge graph perspective on knowledge engineering. SN Computer Science, 4(1), 16. Odoi:10.1007/s42979-022-01429-x
- Aghaei, S., Angele, K., Huaman, E., Bushati, G., Schiestl, M., & Fensel, A. (2022). Interactive search on the web: The story so far. *Information*, 13(7), 324. Ø doi:10.3390/info13070324
- Huaman, E. (2022). Steps to knowledge graphs quality assessment. CoRR, abs/2208.07779. doi:10.48550/arXiv.2208.07779. arXiv: 2208.07779
- Huaman, E., Huaman, J. L., & Huaman, W. (2022). Getting quechua closer to final users through knowledge graphs. CoRR, abs/2208.12608. 6 doi:10.48550/arXiv.2208.12608. arXiv: 2208.12608
- Angele, K., Fensel, D., Huaman, E., Kärle, E., Panasiuk, O., Şimşek, U., ... Wahler, A. (2020). Semantic web empowered e-tourism. *Handbook of e-Tourism*, 1–46.
- Huaman, E., Kärle, E., & Fensel, D. (2020a). Duplication detection in knowledge graphs: Literature and tools. *CoRR*, *abs*/2004.08257. arXiv: 2004.08257. Retrieved from ₱ https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.08257
- Huaman, E., Kärle, E., & Fensel, D. (2020b). Knowledge graph validation. *CoRR*, *abs/2005.01389*. arXiv: 2005.01389. Retrieved from *O* https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.01389

Skills

Coding Java, PHP, Python, LaTeX, ...

Databases Mysql, Graphdb, SPARQL.

Web Dev | HTML, css, JavaScript.

Misc. Academic research, teaching, training, consultation.

Miscellaneous Experience

Selected Projects

2022 - · · · · Coordinator, Qichwabase: It is the Quechua language Knowledge Graph project.

Brings together researchers and Quechua language enthusiasts with the aim of preserving Quechua knowledge, and developing technology for Quechua communities.

Instructor, Science Clubs in Quechua: We develop in a collaborative and multidisciplinary way the use of the Quechua language for the dissemination of different areas of scientific knowledge. See more: http://clubesdecienciaperu.org/project/cdec54/

Documentary, Wikipedia – Die Schwarmoffensive: It explains the possibilities and limits of Wikipedia through conversations with Wikipedia activists, and those who are critical of it. See: https://www.dw.com/de/wikipedia-die-schwarmoffensive/av-61988535

Researcher, WordLift NG project: Develops a new platform to deliver Agentive SEO technology to any website. See more: https://wordlift.io/ng/

Founder, QUIPU [Quechua Language-based Knowledge Graph]: Aims to preserve Quechua knowledge in a structured format. See: https://bit.ly/QUIPUApproach

Researcher, MindLab project: Develops methods and software tools for modelling and implementing scalability for knowledge graphs. See more: https://mindlab.ai/

Awards, Achievements, and Grants

Grant, Wikimedia Foundation for implementing the Reading Wikipedia in the Classroom program (Bringing Wiki project to the Andes), **USA**

Grant, Postdocs to Innovators (p2i) for following an entrepreneurial training course in topics like launching a business, being innovative in industry and academia, **France**

Science Slam Winner, Preserving human knowledge through knowledge graphs by Elwin Huaman, *ScienceSlam2022*, Innsbruck, **Austria**. Read more: www.scienceslam.at

■ Best Project Award, 4th Summer Datathon on Linguistic Linked Open Data (SD-LLOD-22): Dictionary LODification using Wikibase: Quechua language, SD-LLOD-22, Cercedilla, Spain. Read more: https://datathon2022.linkeddata.es/

First Prize, ICTs for Indigenous Languages Hackathon as part of the World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS 2022), *UNESCO*, France. https://bit.ly/WSIS-winner

Best Paper Award, Knowledge Graphs and Semantic Web Conference (KGSWC2021): Towards Knowledge Graphs Validation through Weighted Knowledge Sources, KGSWC2021, Online, Thailand

Finalists phase, Aporta Challenge 2019: Ideas competition, *Ministry of Economy and Business*, Spain. See more: https://bit.ly/aporta-2019

Grant, 1669 Reise- und Forschungsstipendien for attending Wikimania 2019, Austria

First Prize, Smart Destinations hackathon (Hack4SD), World Tourism Organization (UNWTO), Spain

First Prize, University Contest of Talent and Entrepreneurship (CHAMP-U), University of Oviedo, Spain

Miscellaneous Experience (continued)

Grant, Peruvian scientists in Europe (SINAPSIS 2017), **Germany**

Certification

2023 **StudioX: Creating a Course with edX Studio**. Awarded by edX StudioX (edx.org)

Reading Wikipedia in the Classroom Trainers. Awarded by Wikimedia Foundation

Wikibase and Semantic MediaWiki for data-driven semantics. Awarded by the European Commission

2016 Mendeley Advisor. Awarded by ELSEVIER

International Activity

Talks

Presenter: Getting Quechua Closer to Final Users through Knowledge Graphs, at The 9th International Conference on Information Management and Big Data (SIMBig 2022), Peru

- **Invited speaker**: *Qichwabase as a Wikibase instance*, at the Wikibase community user group (Wikibase), Virtual Event, **Germany**. Watch: https://youtu.be/3slzBnISPAk.
- Invited speaker: Publishing Structured Quechua Knowledge (Qichwabase), at the Science Clubs in Quechua, Online, Peru

Presenter: Knowledge Graph Curation: A Practical Framework, at the International Joint Conference on Knowledge Graphs (IJCKG2021), Virtual Event, **Thailand**

- **Presenter**: Towards Knowledge Graphs Validation through Weighted Knowledge Sources, at the Knowledge Graphs and Semantic Web (KGSWC 2021) Conference, **USA**
- **Invited speaker**: *Knowledge Graphs: Past, Present, and Future*, at the COPABISI 2021 Conference, National University of Altiplano, **Peru**
- Invited speaker: Towards an Ecology of Knowledge, at the YACHANA 2021 event, National University of Altiplano, Peru

Invited speaker: Knowledge Graph basado en el idioma Quechua, at the COPAISI 2020 Conference, National University of Altiplano, **Peru**

Presenter: QUIPU: Quechua Language based Knowledge Graph, at the Wikimedia 2019 Conference, University of Stockholm, Sweden

Reviewer tasks

Subreviewer: Semantics and Knowledge track, at the Web Conference (TheWebConf2022), Virtual Event, France

Subreviewer, at the Knowledge Graphs and Semantic Web (KGSWC2021) Conference, USA

Subreviewer, at the 12th International Conference on Knowledge Science, Engineering and Management (KSEM2019), Greece

Subreviewer, at the 12th International A.P. Ershov Informatics Conference (PSI2019), **Russia**

Collaborative events

2021

2022 📕 Organizer: Quechua Wikipedia Editathon, at the Science Clubs in Quechua, Online, Peru

Organizer: Quechua Wikipidiya Editathon, the Endangered Languages Project, Online, USA

Organizer: Workshop on Digital Publishing in Quechua Language, at the Science Clubs in Quechua, Online, Peru